<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Factuality on Lil&#39;Log</title>
    <link>https://lilianweng.github.io/tags/factuality/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Factuality on Lil&#39;Log</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lilianweng.github.io/tags/factuality/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Extrinsic Hallucinations in LLMs</title>
      <link>https://lilianweng.github.io/posts/2024-07-07-hallucination/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lilianweng.github.io/posts/2024-07-07-hallucination/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hallucination in large language models usually refers to the model generating unfaithful, fabricated, inconsistent, or nonsensical content. As a term, hallucination has been somewhat generalized to cases when the model makes mistakes. Here, I would like to narrow down the problem of hallucination to cases where the model output is fabricated and &lt;strong&gt;not grounded&lt;/strong&gt; by either the provided context or world knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two types of hallucination:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In-context hallucination: The model output should be consistent with the source content in context.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extrinsic hallucination: The model output should be grounded by the pre-training dataset. However, given the size of the pre-training dataset, it is too expensive to retrieve and identify conflicts per generation. If we consider the pre-training data corpus as a proxy for world knowledge, we essentially try to ensure the model output is factual and verifiable by external world knowledge. Equally importantly, when the model does not know about a fact, it should say so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post focuses on extrinsic hallucination. To avoid hallucination, LLMs need to be (1) factual and (2) acknowledge not knowing the answer when applicable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
