<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>data on Lil&#39;Log</title>
    <link>https://lilianweng.github.io/tags/data/</link>
    <description>Recent content in data on Lil&#39;Log</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 15:10:30 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lilianweng.github.io/tags/data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Learning with not Enough Data Part 3: Data Generation</title>
      <link>https://lilianweng.github.io/posts/2022-04-15-data-gen/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 15:10:30 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lilianweng.github.io/posts/2022-04-15-data-gen/</guid>
      <description>Here comes the Part 3 on learning with not enough data (Previous: Part 1 and Part 2). Let’s consider two approaches for generating synthetic data for training.
Augmented data. Given a set of existing training samples, we can apply a variety of augmentation, distortion and transformation to derive new data points without losing the key attributes. We have covered a bunch of augmentation methods on text and images in a previous post on contrastive learning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning with not Enough Data Part 2: Active Learning</title>
      <link>https://lilianweng.github.io/posts/2022-02-20-active-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lilianweng.github.io/posts/2022-02-20-active-learning/</guid>
      <description>This is part 2 of what to do when facing a limited amount of labeled data for supervised learning tasks. This time we will get some amount of human labeling work involved, but within a budget limit, and therefore we need to be smart when selecting which samples to label.
Notations Symbol Meaning $K$ Number of unique class labels. $(\mathbf{x}^l, y) \sim \mathcal{X}, y \in \{0, 1\}^K$ Labeled dataset. $y$ is a one-hot representation of the true label.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning with not Enough Data Part 1: Semi-Supervised Learning</title>
      <link>https://lilianweng.github.io/posts/2021-12-05-semi-supervised/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lilianweng.github.io/posts/2021-12-05-semi-supervised/</guid>
      <description>When facing a limited amount of labeled data for supervised learning tasks, four approaches are commonly discussed.
Pre-training + fine-tuning: Pre-train a powerful task-agnostic model on a large unsupervised data corpus, e.g. pre-training LMs on free text, or pre-training vision models on unlabelled images via self-supervised learning, and then fine-tune it on the downstream task with a small set of labeled samples. Semi-supervised learning: Learn from the labelled and unlabeled samples together.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
